[Host] Welcome to Japanese Daily News. I'm Maya. Today is August eighth. Japan's great summer homecoming has begun — this weekend, millions of people are heading back to their hometowns by bullet train, car, and plane for the mid-August holiday. Let's listen.
[News] 今日のニュースです。
[News] お盆をふるさとや行楽地で過ごす人たちの帰省ラッシュが、この週末から本格化しています。
[News] 「帰省」とは、生まれ育ったふるさとに帰ることです。
[News] お盆は、亡くなった家族やご先祖を迎える日本の伝統的な行事で、多くの人がふるさとに帰って、お墓参りをします。
[News] 多くの会社が今月8日ごろから夏休みに入るため、新幹線や高速道路、空の便は、大きな荷物を持った家族連れなどで混雑しています。
[News] JR各社によりますと、ふるさとに向かう下りの新幹線は、8日が混雑のピークで、指定席は午前を中心にほぼ満席となっています。
[News] 東海道新幹線の「のぞみ」は、混雑を避けるため、今月7日から16日まで、すべての座席が指定席になっています。
[News] この期間は自由席がないため、JR東海は、早めに座席を予約するよう呼びかけています。
[News] 高速道路の下りも、8日と9日が混雑のピークで、各地で長い渋滞が予想されています。
[News] 場所によっては、最大でおよそ45キロの渋滞が予想されているところもあります。
[News] 空の便も、国内線の下りは、8日と9日を中心にほぼ満席となっています。
[News] 一方、ふるさとから都市に戻るUターンラッシュのピークは、今月15日と16日になる見込みです。
[News] 各地で厳しい暑さが続いているため、渋滞の中での熱中症や、車のトラブルにも注意が必要です。
[News] 高速道路の会社は、出発する前に渋滞の情報を確認し、時間に余裕を持って行動してほしいと呼びかけています。
[News] 久しぶりにふるさとで家族と過ごす、日本の夏の大切な時間が始まります。
[Host] Now let's break it down, sentence by sentence.
[Slow] お盆をふるさとや行楽地で過ごす人たちの帰省ラッシュが、この週末から本格化しています。
[Host] The homecoming rush — people heading to their hometowns and resorts for the holiday — is in full swing this weekend.
[Vocab] 帰省
[Host] It means returning to your hometown.
[Slow] お盆は、亡くなった家族やご先祖を迎える日本の伝統的な行事で、多くの人がふるさとに帰って、お墓参りをします。
[Host] The holiday is a traditional event for welcoming the spirits of deceased family and ancestors — many people go home and visit the family grave.
[Vocab] 先祖
[Host] It means ancestor.
[Slow] JR各社によりますと、ふるさとに向かう下りの新幹線は、8日が混雑のピークで、指定席は午前を中心にほぼ満席となっています。
[Host] According to the railway companies, outbound bullet trains peak today, the eighth, and reserved seats are almost sold out, especially in the morning.
[Vocab] 満席
[Host] It means fully booked — no seats left.
[Slow] 東海道新幹線の「のぞみ」は、混雑を避けるため、今月7日から16日まで、すべての座席が指定席になっています。
[Host] To ease the crush, the fastest trains on the main Tokyo–Osaka bullet-train line are running with all seats reserved from the seventh through the sixteenth.
[Vocab] 指定席
[Host] It means a reserved seat.
[Slow] 場所によっては、最大でおよそ45キロの渋滞が予想されているところもあります。
[Host] In some places, traffic jams of up to about forty-five kilometers are expected.
[Vocab] 渋滞
[Host] It means a traffic jam.
[Slow] 一方、ふるさとから都市に戻るUターンラッシュのピークは、今月15日と16日になる見込みです。
[Host] Meanwhile, the return rush back to the cities is expected to peak on the fifteenth and sixteenth.
[Vocab] 一方
[Host] It means meanwhile, or on the other hand.
[Slow] 高速道路の会社は、出発する前に渋滞の情報を確認し、時間に余裕を持って行動してほしいと呼びかけています。
[Host] Highway operators are urging drivers to check traffic information before leaving and to allow plenty of extra time.
[Vocab] 余裕
[Host] It means extra room — time or space to spare.
[Host] Let's listen to the whole story one more time.
[News] お盆をふるさとや行楽地で過ごす人たちの帰省ラッシュが、この週末から本格化しています。
[News] 「帰省」とは、生まれ育ったふるさとに帰ることです。
[News] お盆は、亡くなった家族やご先祖を迎える日本の伝統的な行事で、多くの人がふるさとに帰って、お墓参りをします。
[News] 多くの会社が今月8日ごろから夏休みに入るため、新幹線や高速道路、空の便は、大きな荷物を持った家族連れなどで混雑しています。
[News] JR各社によりますと、ふるさとに向かう下りの新幹線は、8日が混雑のピークで、指定席は午前を中心にほぼ満席となっています。
[News] 東海道新幹線の「のぞみ」は、混雑を避けるため、今月7日から16日まで、すべての座席が指定席になっています。
[News] この期間は自由席がないため、JR東海は、早めに座席を予約するよう呼びかけています。
[News] 高速道路の下りも、8日と9日が混雑のピークで、各地で長い渋滞が予想されています。
[News] 場所によっては、最大でおよそ45キロの渋滞が予想されているところもあります。
[News] 空の便も、国内線の下りは、8日と9日を中心にほぼ満席となっています。
[News] 一方、ふるさとから都市に戻るUターンラッシュのピークは、今月15日と16日になる見込みです。
[News] 各地で厳しい暑さが続いているため、渋滞の中での熱中症や、車のトラブルにも注意が必要です。
[News] 高速道路の会社は、出発する前に渋滞の情報を確認し、時間に余裕を持って行動してほしいと呼びかけています。
[News] 久しぶりにふるさとで家族と過ごす、日本の夏の大切な時間が始まります。
[Host] Time for a short quiz. Listen and try to answer.
[Slow] ふるさとに向かう下りの新幹線の混雑のピークは、何日ですか。
[Host] The eighth — today, with reserved seats nearly full in the morning.
[Slow] 東海道新幹線の「のぞみ」は、いつからいつまで、すべての座席が指定席になっていますか。
[Host] From the seventh through the sixteenth of this month.
[Slow] Uターンラッシュのピークは、いつになる見込みですか。
[Host] The fifteenth and sixteenth.
[Host] That's all for today. If you're traveling this weekend, stay cool, be patient in the crowds, and safe travels home. See you tomorrow.
[News] また明日。